Guide to the Herman Landon Vaill Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Herman Landon Vaill collection
1821-1952
MS 519
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.25
The collection consists of papers concerning Elias Boudinot, an Indian whose original name was Galagina, or Buck Oowatie, and who became editor of the "Cherokee Phoenix", New Echota, Cherokee Nation. Early correspondence relates chiefly to Boudinot's marriage to Harriet Gold, and the Gold family controversy over intermarriage with an Indian. Other correspondence relates to the dispute between the Cherokee Nation and the state of Georgia, the Supreme Court decision of 1832, President Jackson's refusal to halt Georgia's annexation of the Cherokee Nation and Boudinot's support of John Ridge, who favored withdrawal of the Cherokee Nation to the West.
Vaill, Herman Landon, d.1870
Existence and Location of Copies
Correspondence, documents, and printed material concerning Elias Boudinot is available on microfilm (49 frames on 1 reel, 35mm.) from Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library, at cost. Order no. HM31.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Dudley L. Vaill, 1962.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Patrons must use FILM HM 31 instead of the originals.
Scope and Contents
The Herman L. Vaill collection contains correspondence (1821-1845) and printed material (1830-1953) relating to the life and activities of Elias Boudinot, Cherokee editor and leader. Early correspondence chiefly concerns Boudinot's marriage to Harriet Gold and to the Gold family controversy over intermarriage with an Indian. Many of the letters are addressed to Herman Vaill, who was a connection by marriage of the Gold family. Other correspondence relates to the dispute between the Cherokee Nation and the State of Georgia, and the Supreme Court decision of 1832 (Worchester vs. Georgia). The division among the Cherokees arising out of President Jackson's refusal to halt Georgia's annexation of the Cherokee lands, and Boudinot's support of the group favoring withdrawal are also discussed. Opinions on the issue are expressed by William Wirt and Boudinot in pamphlets contained in this collection. The other printed material is twentieth century and deals with various aspects of Cherokee history.
The collection was presented to Yale University by Dudley L. Vaill in 1962.
Cherokee Indians; Indians of North America -- Government relations; Interracial marriage; Boudinot, Elias, -1839; Boudinot, Harriett Gold; Ridge, John, 1803-1839; Gold family
- Inventory
  - Correspondence
    - 1821-1823 (Box 1, Folder 1, Reel 1U)
    - 1825 Jun (Box 1, Folder 2, Reel 1U)
    - 1825 Jul (Box 1, Folder 3, Reel 1U)
    - 1825 Aug (Box 1, Folder 4, Reel 1U)
    - 1825 Sep-1826 (Box 1, Folder 5, Reel 1U)
    - 1827-1829 (Box 1, Folder 6, Reel 1U)
    - 1830-1831 (Box 1, Folder 7, Reel 1U)
    - 1832-1837 (Box 1, Folder 8, Reel 1U)
    - 1838-1845, 184? (Box 1, Folder 9, Reel 1U)
  - Printed material
    - William Wirt, Opinion on the Right of the State of Georgia to Extend her Laws over the Cherokee Nation. 27 pp., 1830 (Box 1, Folder 10, Reel 1U)
    - Elias Boudinot, Letters and Other Papers Relating to Cherokee Affairs, Being in Reply to Sundry Publications Authorized by John Ross. 66 pp., 1837 (Box 1, Folder 10, Reel 1U)
    - Henry Thompson Malon, "The Early Nineteenth-Century Missionaries in the Cherokee Country," Tennessee Historical Quarterly, 10, 127-39., 1951 June (Box 1, Folder 10, Reel 1U)
    - "The Cherokee as a Civilized Tribe," The Emory University Quarterly, 8, 225-232., 1952 December (Box 1, Folder 10, Reel 1U)
    - New Echota--Capital of the Cherokee Nation, 1825-1830: A Report to the Georgia Historical Commission, 10 pp., 1953 October 18 (Box 1, Folder 10, Reel 1U)